BUSINESS CONTEXT:
With the enormous growth of computer networks usage and the huge increase in the number of
applications running on top of it, network security is becoming increasingly more important. All
the computer systems suffer from security vulnerabilities which are both technically difficult and
economically costly to be solved by the manufacturers. Therefore, the role of Intrusion Detection
Systems (IDSs), as special-purpose devices to detect anomalies and attacks in the network, is
becoming more important.
The research in the intrusion detection field has been mostly focused on anomaly-based and
misusebased detection techniques for a long time. While misuse-based detection is generally
favored in commercial products due to its predictability and high accuracy, in academic research
anomaly detection is typically conceived as a more powerful method due to its theoretical
potential for addressing novel attacks.
Conducting a thorough analysis of the recent research trend in anomaly detection, one will
encounter several machine learning methods reported to have a very high detection rate of 98%
while keeping the false alarm rate at 1%. However, when we look at the state of the art IDS
solutions and commercial tools, there is no evidence of using anomaly detection approaches, and
practitioners still think that it is an immature technology. To find the reason of this contrast, lots
of research was done done in anomaly detection and considered various aspects such as learning
and detection approaches, training data sets, testing data sets, and evaluation methods.

BUSINESS PROBLEM:
Your task to build network intrusion detection system to detect anamolies and attacks in the
network. There are two problems.
1. Binomial Classification: Activity is normal or attack
2. Multinomial classification: Activity is normal or DOS or PROBE or R2L or U2R
Please note that, currently the dependent variable (target variable) is not definied explicitly.
However, you can use attack variable to define the target variable as required.
DATA AVAILABILITY:
This data is KDDCUP’99 data set, which is widely used as one of the few publicly available data sets
for network-based anomaly detection systems.
For more about data: http://www.unb.ca/cic/datasets/nsl.html
LIST OF COLUMNS FOR THE DATA SET:
["duration","protocol_type","service","flag","src_bytes","dst_bytes","land",
"wrong_fragment","urgent","hot","num_failed_logins","logged_in",
"num_compromised","root_shell","su_attempted","num_root","num_file_creations",
"num_shells","num_access_files","num_outbound_cmds","is_host_login",
"is_guest_login","count","srv_count","serror_rate", "srv_serror_rate",
"rerror_rate","srv_rerror_rate","same_srv_rate", "diff_srv_rate", 
"srv_diff_host_rate","dst_host_count","dst_host_srv_count","dst_host_same_srv_rate",
"dst_host_diff_srv_rate","dst_host_same_src_port_rate",
"dst_host_srv_diff_host_rate","dst_host_serror_rate","dst_host_srv_serror_rate",
"dst_host_rerror_rate","dst_host_srv_rerror_rate","attack", "last_flag"]
BASIC FEATURES OF EACH NETWORK CONNECTION VECTOR
1 Duration: Length of time duration of the connection
2 Protocol_type: Protocol used in the connection
3 Service:Destination network service used
4 Flag: Status of the connection –Normal or Error
5 Src_bytes: Number of data bytes transferred from source to destination in single connection
6 Dst_bytes: Number of data bytes transferred from destination to source in single connection
7 Land: if source and destination IP addresses and port numbers are equal then, this variable takes value 1
else 0
8 Wrong_fragment: Total number of wrong fragments in this connection
9 Urgent:Number of urgent packets in this connection. Urgent packets are packets with the urgent bit
activated
CONTENT RELATED FEATURES OF EACH NETWORK CONNECTION VECTOR
10 Hot: Number of „hot‟ indicators in the content such as: entering a system directory, creating programs
and executing programs
11 Num_failed _logins: Count of failed login attempts
12 Logged_in Login Status: 1 if successfully logged in; 0 otherwise
13 Num_compromised:Number of ``compromised' ' conditions
14 Root_shell:1 if root shell is obtained; 0 otherwise
15 Su_attempted: 1 if ``su root'' command attempted or used; 0 otherwise
16 Num_root: Number of ``root'' accesses or number of operations performed as a root in the connection
17 Num_file_creations:Number of file creation operations in the connection
18 Num_shells:Number of shell prompts
19 Num_access_files:Number of operations on access control files
20 Num_outbound_cmds: Number of outbound commands in an ftp session
21 Is_hot_login: 1 if the login belongs to the ``hot'' list i.e., root or admin; else 0
22 Is_guest_login:1 if the login is a ``guest'' login; 0 otherwise
TIME RELATED TRAFFIC FEATURES OF EACH NETWORK CONNECTION VECTOR
23 Count: Number of connections to the same destination host as the current connection in the past two
seconds
24 Srv_count: Number of connections to the same service (port number) as the current connection in the
past two seconds
25 Serror_rate: The percentage of connections that have activated the flag (4) s0, s1, s2 or s3, among the
connections aggregated in count (23)
26 Srv_serror_rate: The percentage of connections that have activated the flag (4) s0, s1, s2 or s3, among
the connections aggregated in srv_count (24)
27 Rerror_rate: The percentage of connections that have activated the flag (4) REJ, among the connections
aggregated in count (23)
28 Srv_rerror_rate: The percentage of connections that have activated the flag (4) REJ, among the
connections aggregated in srv_count (24)
29 Same_srv_rate: The percentage of connections that were to the same service, among the connections
aggregated in count (23)
30 Diff_srv_rate: The percentage of connections that were to different services, among the connections
aggregated in count (23)
31 Srv_diff_host_ rate: The percentage of connections that were to different destination machines among
the connections aggregated in srv_count (24)
HOST BASED TRAFFIC FEATURES IN A NETWORK CONNECTION VECTOR
32 Dst_host_count: Number of connections having the same destination host IP address
33 Dst_host_srv_ count: Number of connections having the same port number
34 Dst_host_same _srv_rate: The percentage of connections that were to the same service, among the
connections aggregated in dst_host_count (32)
35 Dst_host_diff_ srv_rate: The percentage of connections that were to different services, among the
connections aggregated in dst_host_count (32)
36 Dst_host_same _src_port_rate: The percentage of connections that were to the same source port,
among the connections aggregated in dst_host_srv_c ount (33)
37 Dst_host_srv_ diff_host_rate: The percentage of connections that were to different destination
machines, among the connections aggregated in dst_host_srv_count (33)
38 Dst_host_serro r_rate: The percentage of connections that have activated the flag (4) s0, s1, s2 or s3,
among the connections aggregated in dst_host_count (32)
39 Dst_host_srv_s error_rate: The percent of connections that have activated the flag (4) s0, s1, s2 or s3,
among the connections aggregated in dst_host_srv_c ount (33)
40 Dst_host_rerro r_rate: The percentage of connections that have activated the flag (4) REJ, among the
connections aggregated in dst_host_count (32)
41 Dst_host_srv_r error_rate: The percentage of connections that have activated the flag (4) REJ, among
the connections aggregated in dst_host_srv_c ount (33)
Type Features:
Nominal: Protocol_type(2), Service(3), Flag(4)
Binary: Land(7), logged_in(12), root_shell(14), su_attempted(15), is_host_login(21),, is_guest_login(22)
Numeric:Duration(1), src_bytes(5), dst_bytes(6), wrong_fragment(8), urgent(9), hot(10),
num_failed_logins(11), num_compromised(13), num_root(16), num_file_creations(17),
num_shells(18), num_access_files(19), num_outbound_cmds(20), count(23), srv_count(24), error_rate(25),
srv_serror_rate(26), rerror_rate(27),srv_rerror_rate(28), same_srv_rate(29),diff_srv_rate(30),
srv_diff_host_rate(31), dst_host_count(32), dst_host_srv_count(33), dst_host_same_srv_rate(34),
dst_host_diff_srv_rate(35), dst_host_same_src_port_rate(36), dst_host_srv_diff_host_rate(37),
dst_host_serror_rate(38), dst_host_srv_serror_rate(39), dst_host_rerror_rate(40),
dst_host_srv_rerror_rate(41)

============================================================
- Attack Class
==> DoS
- Attack Type
==> Back, Land, Neptune, Pod,
    Smurf,Teardrop,Apache2, Udpstorm,
    Processtable, Worm (10)
- Attack Class
==> Probe 
- Attack Type
==> Satan, Ipsweep, Nmap, Portsweep, Mscan,
    Saint (6)
- Attack Class
==> R2L
- Attack Type
==> Guess_Password, Ftp_write, Imap, Phf,
    Multihop, Warezmaster, Warezclient, Spy,
    Xlock, Xsnoop, Snmpguess, Snmpgetattack,
    Httptunnel, Sendmail, Named (16)
- Attack Class
==> U2R 
- Attack Type
==> Buffer_overflow, Loadmodule, Rootkit, Perl,
    Sqlattack, Xterm, Ps (7)

=============================================================

ATTACK CLASS
1. DOS: Denial of service is an attack category, which depletes the victim‟s resources thereby making it
unable to handle legitimate requests –e.g. syn flooding. Relevant features: “source bytes” and “percentage
of packets with errors”
2. Probing: Surveillance and other probing attack‟s objective is to gain information about the remote victim
e.g. port scanning. Relevant features: “duration of connection” and “source bytes”
3. U2R: unauthorized access to local super user (root) privileges is an attack type, by which an attacker uses
a normal account to login into a victim system and tries to gain root/administrator privileges by exploiting
some vulnerability in the victim e.g. buffer overflow attacks. Relevant features: “number of file creations”
and “number of shell prompts invoked,”
4. R2L: unauthorized access from a remote machine, the attacker intrudes into a remote machine and gains
local access of the victim machine. E.g. password guessing Relevant features: Network level features –
“duration of connection” and “service requested” and host level features - “number of failed login
attempts".